<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <string name="app_name">actNOW</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_open">Open navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_close">Close navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="title_activity_story">story</string>
    <string name="title_activity_splash">SplashActivity</string>
    <string name="title_activity_about">AboutActivity</string>
    <string name="title_activity_detail_story">DetailStoryActivity</string>
    <string name="tvDetailTitleString">title</string>
    <string name="storyAuthorString">author</string>
    <string name="share">share</string>
    <string name="action_signin">Sign up to actNOW</string>
    <string name="action_blog">blog</string>
    <string name="aboutUsStep1">actNOW is a platform for investigators and journalists to report their findings on corruption and human rights issues.</string>
    <string name="aboutUsStep2">In response to injustice, users can petition decision makers and share stories with friends.</string>
    <string name="swipeLeft">Our first documentary recently launched. Swipe left arrow to see our latest work.</string>
    <string name="swipeLeft2"> to see our latest work.</string>
    <string name="aboutUsMessage">What we do and why...</string>
    <string name="contentDescription">actNOW Image</string>
    <string name="petitionTitle">Title fashion axe freegan direct trade Neutra kitsch Ennui.</string>
    <string name="spell_of_albino_story"><![CDATA[Albinism is a non-contagious, genetically inherited disorder, affecting about 1 in 20,000 men and women around the world, regardless of ethnicity and geographical location. Sufferers are afflicted by a congenital absence of melanin, a pigmentation defect in the hair, skin and eyes that causes vulnerability to sun exposure and bright light. Many have very poor vision as a consequence and in tropical countries especially they can be vulnerable to skin cancers if unprotected from the sun.

What albinism is absolutely not, is an indication that the afflicted person is any way invested with magical powers.

Though it might seem absurdly obvious, the point is worth stating so starkly because in parts of sub-Saharan Africa especially, albinos have traditionally faced discrimination and prejudice - innocent victims of a still widespread belief that the condition is in some way associated with the supernatural. To some, a white-skinned African person is seen as a kind of phantom or ghost, who rather than die will dissolve or disappear with the wind and rain. As a result, in some communities, albinos have been feared, shunned and socially marginalised.

Over the last five years in Tanzania, however, the situation has become much, much worse, with albinos increasingly subjected to murder and mutilation because of a completely spurious myth that albino body parts are effective in witchcraft rituals. Despite international outrage and repeated attempts by the Tanzanian government to stamp out this truly appalling practice, since it first came to light many albinos have been hunted down and attacked purely for their limbs and organs. Indeed the incidents seem to be increasing. Since 2008, at least 62 albinos have been killed in Tanzania, 16 have been violently assaulted and had their limbs amputated and the bodies of 12 albinos have been exhumed from graves and dismembered.

Against this background, it is perhaps not surprising that estimates of the numbers of albinos in Tanzania vary significantly. Officially there are around 5,000 registered, but the country’s Albino Association says the real number is in excess of 150,000. They say that many albinos are still kept hidden by their families because of the stigma some associate with the condition or because of fear that they might be attacked.

In this remarkable episode of Africa Investigates, Tanzanian journalist Richard Mgamba, albino community representative Isaack Timothy and Ghanaian investigative journalist Anas Aremeyaw Anas set out to discover what lies behind these sickening attacks and to uncover and confront some of those behind the grotesque trade in body parts for witchcraft rituals.

In the process they meet two albino children, victims of vicious assaults that occurred in the weeks the film was being made. One of them is a 12-year-old boy who had part of his hand cut off, allegedly with the connivance of his father who is now in police custody and awaiting trial. The other is a 16-year-old girl whose left arm was hacked off by a stranger with a machete.

But Anas, who goes undercover in the guise of a businessman seeking to get rich, also comes face to face with a witchdoctor who tries to sell him a potion containing ground up albino body parts. Not surprisingly, when the offer is made, Anas makes his abhorrence very plain.

Right from the start of this film, viewers may find some of the images disturbing.]]></string>
    <string name="spirit_child_story"><![CDATA[Thousands of children have been killed in Ghana because the communities they are born into believe they are evil spirits.
				 When I first heard about this I could not believe it was happening in my country in the 21st century. 
				 The practice originally emerged as a way for poor families to deal with deformed or disabled children that they cannot look after.
				  These families approach village elders known as concoction men and inform them that they suspect their child to be a so-called spirit child. 
				 The concoction man then takes the father of the child to visit a soothsayer who confirms whether or not the child is truly evil, without ever actually laying eyes on them.  
				 Once this confirmation has been received, the concoction man brews a poisonous liquid from local roots and herbs and force-feeds it to the child, almost always resulting in death. 
				 Over time, this practice has become a perceived solution to any problems a family might be having at the time of a child\'s birth. 
				 By blaming the child for sickness in the family, or the father\'s inability to find work or provide money to support his dependents, 
				 these communities have found an otherworldly explanation for their problems. 
				 In this highly patriarchal society it enables heads of family to pass the blame for their struggles onto someone else. 
				 And by branding the child a spirit from outside the family, they can disassociate themselves and feel justified in murdering their own offspring, 
				 while telling those around them that now all will be well - the evil presence is gone.  But infanticide has always been a crime against humanity. 
				 I believe there is plenty of evidence of infanticide in the history of all human societies and its continued and widespread practice makes a mockery 
				 of the democratic credentials of the countries, including mine, where this crime still takes place. Many forms of civic engagement and advocacy have 
				 been used in a bid to eradicate this practice in Ghana and other West African nations. Sadly though, the limited efficacy of such techniques is 
				 illustrated by the fact that today children are still being killed in this way.  Ready to spill blood in the name of tradition.  
				 And sometimes a strong focus on understanding and education when dealing with traditional practices can distance us from the reality of a situation; 
				 it can place us in an ivory tower where we fail to engage with the true manner in which those involved are behaving. Far from acting like a 
				 man fulfilling a sad but necessary duty, the concoction man I hired to kill my fictitious child for the purposes of this film was excited; 
				 his eyes pinned wide with zeal as he went about preparing for the task at hand. He laughed and joked about his previous experience, telling me 
				 about how he had recently killed a 12-year-old girl by tricking her into drinking his concoction and boasting about how effective his methods are.
				  Without knowing the context, any casual observer would surely consider his disposition nothing short of murderous. While I understand that he 
				 was misguided - ready to spill innocent blood in the name of tradition - I also strongly believe that, no matter what the circumstances, 
				 where children are being murdered the state must step in to punish those responsible in the same way that the citizens of any developed democracy 
				 would expect it to. That is not to say that some understanding cannot be afforded to the concoction men and the communities that continue to 
				 practice these rituals. Unlike those with the benefit of technology who can see a badly developed fetus and terminate it before birth, the 
				 mothers whose babies are killed in northern Ghana have no such options. They may find themselves giving birth to a child only to discover 
				 that it is not normal: it will never be accepted and will always be a burden on those around it. In the absence of technology or a refuge 
				 for mother and child to escape to, the concoction man is the only solution. As a result, the parents perceive him as a saviour; the only 
				 one who can deliver them from enduring further hardship. And the concoction men in turn thrive on the standing and power this affords them 
				 in the community. When we think of slavery or the burning of alleged witches, these crimes against humanity were only eradicated when key actors 
				 in government decided to take a stand. By declaring these practices as unacceptable and threatening those who continue to perpetrate them
				  with prosecution, governments have brought about the abolition of centuries-old traditions in a relatively short space of time.  Permitting 
				 evil to triumph over good  From northern Ghana, where the spirit child story is set, through Burkina Faso, Benin and parts of Nigeria,
				  countless babies are killed based on age-old cultural beliefs. But despite this, we were unable to find any evidence of previous arrests 
				 for these crimes.  During the three weeks that I worked on this story, I came across 10 men who were willing to kill a baby for spiritual 
				 reasons. They were easy to find. Yet when I asked a senior police officer why no arrests have been made, his response was]]></string>
    <string name="petition_signed">Your petition will be e-mailed to President John Dramani Mahama’s Chief of Staff Prosper Bani</string>
    <string name="petition_signed_thanku">Thank You for acting NOW. Encourage your friends to do the same!</string>
    <string name="petition_signed_success">Success!</string>
    <string name="storyTitle1">Enemies of the Nation: The dark secrets of Tema Harbour</string>
    <string name="storySource1">Source: New Crusading Guide | February 2, 2011</string>
    <string name="storySource2">Source: edition.myjoyonline.com | August 17, 2009</string>
    <string name="storyTitle2">Chinese sex mafia busted</string>
    <string name="storyTitle3">Journalist Face-to-Face with Chinese Sex Mafia</string>
    <string name="storySource3">Source: ghanaweb.com | March 13, 2009</string>
    <string name="storySourceAnas">Source: Anas Aremeyaw Anas | April 2014</string>

    <string-array name="drawer_menu_array">
        <item>Sign In</item>
        <item>Documentary</item>
        <item>Feed</item>
        <item>About</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="countries_array">
        <item>Ashanti (Kumasi)</item>
        <item>Brong Ahafo (Sunyani)</item>
        <item>Central (Cape Coast)</item>
        <item>Eastern (Koforidua)</item>
        <item>Greater Accra (Accra)</item>
        <item>Northern (Tamale)</item>
        <item>Upper East (Bolgatanga)</item>
        <item>Upper West (Wa)</item>
        <item>Volta (Ho)</item>
        <item>Western (Sekondi-Takoradi)</item>
    </string-array>

    <!--Stories-->
    <string name="enemies_of_the_nation_story"><![CDATA[A veritable commercial beehive; the economic nerve centre of Ghana, sits on the shores of the Atlantic and overlooks the bubbling big blue sea. The sea breeze seems to have been directed purposely to produce a calming effect on the crammed and torrid atmosphere and on the bristling pace of business. The national flag, the Customs flag, and that of the Ports and Harbours go fluttering and flying at full mast. Gallant men and women resplendent in their uniform, complete with their berets embossed with the sacred Coat of Arms, walk around in high morale. Businessmen in their tuxedoes and clearing agents crisscross, moving from office to office with an air of tenacious dedication.

Do not be deceived, some of these men in Ghana’s iconic harbour city are busily stealing from the most fertile vineyards of the motherland.

The nation’s trusted farmhands at the Harbour have appropriated the farmland and its produce and denied their landlord (Ghana) the benefits due him. The Tema Harbour has been turned into a goldmine for some greedy security officials who are threatening to strip the mine facility to satisfy their selfish ends. Many officers from CEPS, the Ghana Police Service, National Security and the Ghana Ports and Habours Authority would do all it takes in the scramble to possess a piece of the prize.

It is a dark and murky world at the Tema Harbour, as these security officials collaborate with some clearing agents to steal money belonging to the state through tax evasion, bribery and personal greed, thereby defeating the nation’s revenue mobilization efforts. Invariably, potential investors, importers and ordinary Ghanaians are made to bear the brunt of the selfishness and greed exhibited by these officers and agents because prices are passed over.

These discoveries follow over three months of investigation by The New Crusading GUIDE into the operations of the Tema Harbour. Posing as a clearing agent under the name “Oblitey Sowah”, alias “Koose” from “Tiger Shipping agency”, Anas Aremeyaw Anas, together with a team of agents, obtained secret video footage on the daily cases of bribery and corruption that greet any importer or businessperson who calls at the port. Most importers are made to face the harsh realities of delays, payment of illegal fees, destruction and stealing of their goods as well as the sheer greed displayed by some security officers.

The investigations also brought to light multiple cases of bribery, corruption, stealing, several cases of collusion between security officials and clearing agents as well as loss of goods belonging to importers as a result of inadequate security measures at the facility. The investigation uncovered some of the worst forms of bribery and corruption, lack of professionalism and glaring examples of stealing by these security officials at the port.

Amidst all these corrupt activities, many agents have devised ways of adding the cost of bribe charges to the fees they usually charge importers. As a result, people who import goods into the country through the harbour go through unspeakable frustrations, not least the payment of huge sums of illegal charges which end up in the pockets of private individuals. In the process, it takes months to clear goods from the harbour. Sometimes, the nightmares of these importers are climaxed by the loss of their goods through theft or damages through mishandling. Over the years, there have been many reports of how unattractive the Harbour has become, with many importers channeling their frustrations through diverse ways. It is striking how very little has changed in the system.

The New Crusading GUIDE also got access into the Customs Electronic system – a repository of all transactions that go on at the port – where we found very worrying cases of tax exemptions and unrecovered debts owed to the state worth billions of cedis. It brought to the fore many cases of tax exemption offered in the name of the Office of the President over the years. Many other exemptions were given out to individuals and companies on condition of “Awaiting Parliamentary Approval”.

Here, we discovered that monies lost in bribery, corruption and some tax exemptions could help usher Ghana into an era of freedom from foreign donors.

DODGY “AWAITING PARLIAMENTARY APPROVAL”, THAT NEVER WENT TO PARLIAMENT

Many Businessmen and friends of politicians have over the years used their association to parliamentarians to evade taxes whenever they clear goods from the Tema Harbour. These individuals sometimes import goods in their names for family members and their companies.

Undoubtedly, the use of the name of parliament has resulted in the state losing millions Cedis, as some government officials over the years deliberately abuse the system to clear goods for their business cronies.

Our checks also revealed that even when the code is used to clear genuine goods, the much-awaited parliamentary approval never comes to validate it. It was horrifying to realize that some of these people never went to parliament for approval.

Between March 2007 and December 2009, over GH¢ 900 million worth of tax exemptions was granted to some individuals and institutions in the name of “Parliament”. These tax exemptions were given out for goods ranging from medical equipment, household items, educational items and vehicles; with beneficiaries across public and private entities. Further figures obtained between January and November 2010 indicate that approximately GH¢ 17.9 million was lost by the state as a result of these special permits in the name of Parliament.

Parliament is constitutionally mandated to handle all tax issues that border on finances. Part of Article 174(1) of the constitution under chapter 13, sub-headed “finance” states that “no taxation shall be imposed otherwise than by under the authority of an act of parliament”. In this light, no taxes can be levied on anybody unless it is done under an act of parliament.

Although exemptions are given for special reasons based on parliamentary approval, The New Crusading GUIDE found out that the system was being abused by some individuals and organizations who always use the name of parliament to evade taxes. For the past six years, Parliament does not have any record of some of these exemptions.

In an interview with The New Crusading GUIDE, Chairman of the Finance Committee in parliament, Hon James Avedzi said although parliament has conferred the power of granting exemptions on the Ministry of Finance, it does not have an idea which individuals or organizations have been granted exemptions over these years.

“l have not seen anything like that as a deputy ranking member of the committee in 2007-2008 and as chairman from 2009 to 2010. l have not seen anything”, he admitted. Although he conceded that “the Ministry of Finance [is supposed] to do that on daily basis and report back to parliament after a period of time”. He was unable to state what period of time parliament is supposed to revise such exemptions.

When presented with the evidence of exemptions to institutions and individuals as we discovered on the Electronic system, Hon James Avedzi simply said, “l will not talk about the value that we have seen because l do not know what goes into that 18 million Ghana Cedis you are talking about but it is possible that there is something like that you can see from the system”.

THE WIDENING JAWS OF DEATH AND HOW OUR BROTHERS IN THE DIASPORA ARE TREATED

Many Ghanaians leave the shores of the land to go and work in foreign lands in order to return someday to build a better life for their kith and kin. These men and women toil in sweatshops and endure harsh conditions in foreign lands just to provide for themselves and their families. They return to Ghana, their homeland, only to have their hopes dashed at the Tema Harbour. Long held dreams are blown apart, as they are not able to get hold of their valuable possessions.

It usually is a tale of toil defeated by treachery, as Ghanaians who return from the Diaspora are always greeted with the grim reality of seeing their hard-earned properties stolen and destroyed by men at the Tema Harbour. When this happens, they are treated by port officials with so much disrespect and heartlessness. It is assumed that these Ghanaians have a lot to spend, little time to stay and fight for their goods. They [goods] are never found, although they spend sums of money in wearisome clearing process. Many are distressed in the process; those who endure usually leave the shores of Ghana with sad songs about their beloved country. It is a disturbing cycle of evil trumping goodwill.

Becky Mensah is a Ghanaian-born philanthropist based in Canada. In January last year, Becky, with the help of some friends and benevolent institutions in Canada, collected some materials to help students of an educational institution in Cape Coast.

They shipped a 40-foot container loaded with educational materials, computers, sewing machines, food items and a boxful of household effects to help support Ghanaian school children.

Although the container, which was addressed in the name of the Paramount chief of Cape Coast, was originally destined for the Takoradi Harbour, it never arrived. Becky eventually had to travel from Canada to Ghana to locate it. After a long search, the container records were finally found at the Tema Harbour in June 2010.

She was asked by Port authorities to pay the necessary duties in order to have her container released. With the help of her agents, she paid the required fees, totaling about GHc 5000. Yet, it took another five months and a trip back to Ghana to see her container. When she finally got access to it in November 2010, it had been broken into, with almost half the humanitarian items stolen.

“When we got there, the customs officer checked without tag on our papers, the tag number and check the thing that closes the container, the seal that seals the container and the numbers did not match but the thing that was to my surprise was one of the carrier there just got closer to it and he just wiggled the thing and the whole thing opened”, she told The New Crusading GUIDE in an interview.

Among other things, three laptops, 800 stuffed backpacks for students, 68 bedspreads, 4 sewing machines, a boxful of household items and several bottles of water were stolen. Nobody gave her any answers and she had to make do with a half-empty container which she took to Cape Coast to support needy students. Becky has finally returned to Canada after this trouble with port authorities. In all, she lost goods worth over one 120,000 dollars.

When she approached security officials at the port, they refused to pay any attention to her. “I was actually shocked, but the customs guy never said a word. l started to complain to him and he just walked away”, she said with tearful eyes. “There was a group of them sitting under a tree and l said to them ‘will you guys help us’, they just stared at our face and didn’t say one word. It was so humiliating and painful, these people in uniform at the Harbour, we their customers were standing there and saying ‘can you see what has happened to us’; our container is almost empty. But all four of them sat there and just stared at us as l looked on helplessly”.

Like Becky, countless individuals have harrowing tales of abuse they endure when they ship goods from various destinations to Ghana through the Tema port.

Emmanuel Ahulu, a Ghanaian who recently returned from Virginia in the United States of America also had a similar story. After shipping a brand new car, together with goods through the Tema Harbour, Emmanuel got to Ghana only to realize that all his goods were stolen and his car badly dented. This was after he had engaged the services of a clearing agent, done the necessary documentations and got assured that “things were under control”.

“Everything in the car actually was stolen. l couldn’t find anything, items that were bought and packed in the car actually in their brand new state – in boxes and in bags – everything was gone, nothing had been left”, he told The New Crusading GUIDE. “The car trunk was broken and they entered it and took every item that l brought”, he added.

When he approached port officials, Emmanuel was greeted with the same fate as Becky: he could not get anyone to listen to his plight. He has since threatened legal action.

“l believe that the next line of action is that the authority be held responsible, whoever is in charge of those terminals, whoever is in charge of those containers or all the cars that come in. l think he should be held responsible and he should be accountable for if that is done, l believe very well we are going to get somewhere; we are going to get to the bottom of this”, he said.

It appears security officers who are mandated to take care of the port have failed woefully in the performance of their duties. Apart from the numerous cases of bribe-taking we witnessed, little can be said about the role these officials play at the port. Sometimes, they look on as agents and some people break into and sell goods in containers belonging to some importers in the full glare of the public.

Johnson Clarkson, an investor from the United Kingdom also faced a similar ordeal at the port. In an interview with The New Crusading GUIDE, he narrated how over hundred bicycles which he shipped from the United Kingdom to support Ghanaian farmers in the Brong Ahafo Region got missing.

“After going through hell to pay all those duties, I was bewildered when I found more than half of my goods missing”, he told the paper. He has since returned to his country, after he could not get any response from the Harbour Police and port authorities.

Nii Lantey Okunka Bannerman, a Ghanaian living in the Diaspora, once posted an article on Ghanaweb titled “Belly of the Beast”. It was a recount of his experiences in clearing a car at the Tema Harbour sometime in 2005. Nii Lantey, in an apparent state of exasperation, wrote about how his car got “trapped” in the “jaws of death” [the Tema Harbour], citing an unending web of bribe taking, bureaucratic bottlenecks and acts of collusion which hamper the smooth clearing of goods from the port.

More than five years on, it appears little has been done to turn the toxic-breathing jaws of the harbour into a friendly environment for importers. The cases of Becky Mensah, Emmanuel Ahulu are the recurring features in the unchanging script of the Harbour story.

<b>THE CANADIAN SAGA</b></br>

Following the experiences of Becky Mensah, The New Crusading GUIDE made a trip to Canada to assess the Canadian situation. True to Becky’s accounts, the ports in Canada – including Port Calgary, where she shipped the container from – are orderly and well managed. There is an absence of corruption and most of the systems are automated. It is difficult to find port officials demanding bribes from importers and exporters. Also, goods shipped to meet Humanitarian needs are exempted from all taxes or duties.

There were also no reports of stealing as exists in the Ghanaian setting. Undoubtedly, Canada provides an example for Ghanaian officials in-charge of the ports to emulate. Like other developed countries, the Canadian ports have very efficient systems which make shipping less stressful.

In an interview with Prof Atsu Amegashie, an Associate Proffessor in the Department of Economics at the University of Guelph in Canada, he stated that the problem of revenue leakages can only be solved if the authorities take serious actions.

“There’s the need for a committed leadership, that is willing to incentivize and induce agents to go after corrupt officials who are in charge of tax administration”, he opined.

The Professor, who is also a Ghanaian, maintained that the Canadian situation offers a shining example for Ghanaians to follow.

<b>OFFICE OF THE PRESIDENT AND THE TYCOONS</b>

Beyond the disturbing spate of corruption between security officials and clearing agents, the abuse of the name of Parliament and the fate of those from the Diaspora who clear goods through the Harbour, The New Crusading GUIDE also uncovered a tide of sleazy deals which stretch even higher. The “Office of the President” has also been used over the years as a rubber stamp by certain individuals and organizations to rob the state of its needed revenue.

Section 44 of the Customs, Excise &amp; Preventive Service (Management) Law provides the legal basis for CEPS to grant exemption from the payment of import duty to privileged persons, like THE PRESIDENT. This position is exemplified as Tariff No. 3AF.1 of PART A of the THIRD SCHEDULE of the CEPS Tariff at page 653.

Thus, “OFFICE OF THE PRESIDENT”, which is under the Ministry of Presidential Affairs, is different from "THE PRESIDENT”. Office of the President does not enjoy any duty and tax exemption under the laws of Ghana. The exemption covers items imported or purchased locally by the President for his personal use, not items imported or purchased locally by the state. These exempted items are the personal property of the President. For the present purposes, these are items imported or purchased by the person who, for the time being is the President of Ghana. These are items that he will continue to own, even when he is no longer President of the Republic of Ghana.

For instance, an official who works in the office of the President cannot clear his goods for free simply because he works in the office of the President. The New Crusading GUIDE however, discovered that the rights given to the President were abused by senior officials of various governments. Goods, which had nothing to do with the President’s person, had found themselves being cleared in the name of the office of the President by various government officials. This is done usually without the President’s knowledge.

Discoveries on the system total exemptions under the code, indicated that the office of the president comes to GHC14, 190, 336 (an equivalent of 9, 511, 000 dollars). An examination of the entries as sighted had questionable declarations, including luxury vehicles imported under the name of a member of parliament, assorted used vehicles, used clothing, fish meal, second hand air conditioners, second hand sewing machines and rather non-presidential materials.

“I am shocked at this list because I know our Presidents do not use used cars. I also do not know any of our Presidents who has a poultry farm. So why these second hand cars and imported fishmeal by the Office of the President?” asked an official at the Finance Ministry when he saw the list of special permits in the name of the President.

We found out that, the Ministry of Finance had also had its fair share of granting exemptions. It had granted permit for the clearance of goods without permit to the tune of about 5million Ghana Cedis (an equivalent of over 3 million two hundred dollars).

<b>GHANA’S GOLDFIELD STRIP-MINED BY MEN IN UNIFORM PAID TO SECURE IT</b>

The police, Customs Excise and Preventive Service, Ghana Ports and Harbours Authority Security, officials from National Security are fully engaged in bribery and corruption. They usually demand specific amounts from agents who are found evading tax through mis-classification, under-valuation or over-valuation of goods. Sometimes, they demand money before allowing entry into certain points within the port or before signing documents for the agents.

It is common to see security officials admonishing agents to learn how to give bribes. “Without this, you cannot succeed in this business”, they usually say. On one occasion, we encountered a Senior CEPS officer named Mr. Kwakye at the CEPS laboratory who demanded money before approving our goods. When The New Crusading GUIDE could not pay the money the officer demanded, this is part of what transpired:

<b>LAB MAN:</b> You! See you should always remember that, this is like when you come, next time come here again, and then you have become our friend. You see!
<b>TIGER:</b> Yeah! Yeah!
<b>LAB MAN:</b> So how much are you saying?
<b>TIGER:</b> Boss! Boss! Let me give you GHC 50
<b>LAB MAN:</b> How much? GHC 50, add something
<b>TIGER:</b> Pardon sir?
<b>LAB MAN:</b> Add something; is that all you have?
<b>TIGER:</b> That is why I am saying…
<b>LAB MAN:</b> You cannot say anything
<b>TIGER:</b> We can be saying something which will be looking so provocative, you being in the system and this being our first time, you can tell us this is how we are doing it and we also say oh! So far as this is our first time, Boss we, we are now becoming friends.
<b>LAB MAN:</b> You just make it GHC 100
<b>TIGER:</b> GHC100?
<b>LAB MAN:</b> Nice lady and nice like this, you are thinking of opening your company in the future, you have to know certain things on the ground, you see!

<b>TIGER:</b> Yes sir!
<b>LAB MAN:</b> But if you start with your hands like this…
<b>TIGER:</b>Oh! No sir that is not that <b>LAB MAN:</b> If you open your company things will not go well

On another occasion, this reporter met a GPHA Security official who demanded money before allowing him entry into the port:

<b>SECURITY MAN:</b> You be agent?
<b>TIGER:</b>Yeah!
<b>SECURITYMAN:</b> Then you get money, bring am make l chop inside. Yes! Bring your requirements. I go chop ooh!!
<b>TIGER:</b>You go chop?
<b>SECURITYMAN:</b> I go chop small one
<b>TIGER:</b>No! Problem
<b>OFFICER:</b> No be big one

Clearly, the case of bribery and corruption as it exists between agents and CEPS has far-reaching consequences as far as national revenue mobilization is concerned. As these shady deals come to a head, current and potential investors are seriously frustrated as agents normally include the proverbial “Bribe-fees” to their charges. Though most importers overlook the illegality and pay these monies, they sometimes go through hell to get access to their goods. The cases of Becky Mensah and Emmanuel Ahulu typify the order at the Tema Harbour.

<b>BETWEEN CORRUPTION AND FOREIGN AID</b>

Financial and policy experts have suggested that Ghana could wean itself off donor support if those in charge of Ghana’s ports city worked hard enough and cut out the corruption and negligence. The exemption system granted under the name of Parliament and the Office of the President has been abused, and this has taken a toll on the National treasury.

“The situation where it seems as if these exemptions were being abused instead of bringing in materials and the rest that will prop up our economy becomes worrying”, says Dr. Lloyd Amoah, a policy analyst and professor at Ashesi University. To put an end to the incessant borrowing by government, he maintains that the Harbour, as an entry point, “provides a lot of revenue and so it means that fundamentally for a developing country this ought to be looked at critically”.

A senior fellow at IMANI Ghana, Kofi Bentil, also argued, that “If we manage our ports well, we could actually make more money out of the port system than we are making out of cocoa for instance”.

He continued, “If we were to make services a central issue in this economy, it is possible that we will improve the economy, l means government revenue, and actually serve the sub-regions, and one of the areas l identified as a note for such service economy is the port system. Between Tema and Takoradi port, we can actually establish a system which will serve the whole West Africa sub-region”.

The question of Ghana’s inability to meet its revenue targets is more an issue of mismanagement and corruption rather than the lack of resources.

The World Bank Country director to Ghana, Ishac Diwan, believes Ghana’s revenue mobilization efforts needs to be improved.

“ The various taxes need to be linked together in a database so that, knowing how much VAT, how much volume of business which is useful for the VAT, informs the tax authority about incomes and profits so that cooperate taxes can be collected. So, there is the need for more efficiency in terms of the different services working together and finally, also, facilitating the entry of business into the formal economy”, he says.

“It is very important to close the loop falls and to have a more disciplined system. There are just too many exemptions that have been granted left and right through lobbying by the various industries, sectors, companies”, he points out.

Coming up: Tomorrow, we bring you the story of how GCNet, Ghana Ports and Harbours Authority (GPHA) and Destination Inspection Companies have contributed to the loss of huge sums of money belonging to the State. The electronic system, the Ghana Customs Management System (GCMS) is the repository of all transactions engaged in by both genuine and dubious businesspersons across the length and breadth of the country. It is only a select few of special people who know the secrets and can interpret the electronic system. We got in there and found out all the dirty tricks used to evade tax and starve mother Ghana. The story takes you through the raw deal that the state suffers as a result of acts by these institutions. It is Part two of the Enemies of the Nation. We also bring you details of how Deputy CEPS Commissioner, Annie Anipa played merry-go-round with The New Crusading GUIDE in the unfolding saga.]]></string>

    

<string name="journalist_face_to_face_with_chinese_sex_mafia"><![CDATA[Clash Of The Titans, Investigative Journalist Face-to-Face with Chinese Sex Mafia ‘Dons’.

<b>HARDCORE DOSSEIR IN COURT</b>

Not even theatre goers could have had a better deal than the drama that unfolded last Tuesday in an Accra Circuit Court under the gavel of Justice Elizabeth Ankomah when The New Crusading Guide’s Ace Investigative reporter, Anas Aremeyaw Anas, came face-to-face with the ‘dons’ of the Chinese sex mafia. The court had asked the reporter to come and play the audio and video evidence he had gathered in his six months investigations into the operations of the Chinese sex mafia within the West African sub region.

The three dons, James Xu Jin, (first accused) Chou Xiou Ving, (second accused) and Sam Shan Zifan (third accused) were visibly shocked when the reporter started playing on a big screen, their activities of engaging the Chinese girls for exploitation.

They could not dispute the content of the video “that is Sam taking money from that Whiteman and delivering that Chinese girl to the client for sexual exploitation. I am the one standing there in white with a bow- tie disguised as a bar tender and serving the alleged trafficker with beer in the hotel” Anas explained while playing the evidence to the court.

Counsel for the accused persons Mr. B. O K.Johnson, Police Prosecutor ASP Ms Mary Agbozo were all present when Anas who was also the complainant in the case showed the evidence. Earlier Anas had tendered 8 audio clips, 2 videos, 9 transcript of conversations and photographs all marked as exhibits to the court.

In his evidence- in- chief, Anas narrated how he conducted his investigations to the court, pointing out that his investigations were motivated by his interest in saving humanity. He narrated how he posed as a bar tender in a hotel to obtain evidence of the girls being sexually exploited. He explained that he befriended a lady in the residence of the traffickers in order to get information on their operations at their La residence (Agyeman) a suburb of Accra.

He told the court that, he monitored the girls for over six months within which he saw them being sent out to casinos, hotels and saw men also coming out from the residence of the accused persons. He also added that, one of his sources had also been having conversations with the victims, in connection with their activities and had on tape all the conversations.

During the cross examination by the defense counsel, Mr. B. O K. Johnson, Anas (witness) indicated that his friendship with the house maid of the accused persons was not amorous, but one of his ways as an undercover journalist to get information to prove his case.

He denied an allegation that the housemaid of the accused smuggled him into the house saying “I was smuggled into the room by a source found condoms in the house, and picked only one which was unused from the first room”.

Defense counsel also accused the witness of desiring to have sex with the girl he befriended in the residence of the traffickers but could not succeed because, James Xu Jin, (first accused) intervened and truncated the process. He said that witness had some hatred for first accused for truncating his sexual encounter and thereby decided to go undercover to do story to humiliate his client.

“I put it to you that you wanted to have sex with the Chinese girls and when they refused, you developed hatred for them and thereby did this investigation, your investigation was borne by malice towards my clients”. The defense counsel told the court. “It is not so my lord”, Anas answered, the “Chinese girls do not have sex with blacks”.

Mr. B. O. K Johnson also told the court that the money that was charged in the second operation of the witness was $100 not $150 as claimed by the witness saying “I put it to you that the money which was paid in the second operation was $100 and not $150”

All seven victims who testified in court were seen trembling anytime they recounted the harrowing experiences they went through during their sexual activities. They therefore pleaded to be protected by the court for fear of being killed by the accused persons, who they regarded as very powerful.

The girls, (names withheld) gave account of the fact that, Jin brought them to Ghana and for that matter they owed him and had to work to pay for their air fares and other traveling documents which Jin secured for them to facilitate their trip to Ghana.

One of the victims, an 18 year old girl from Shangai in China could not hold back her tears as she narrated her story in the presence of the judge, journalists, prosecutors and defense counsel in chambers. The accused persons who were made to stand close to the door to enable them hear the proceedings were shocked beyond description. She stated that she was deceived by the accused persons that she was coming to Ghana to work in a Chinese restaurant only to end up in prostitution.

According to the teenage girl, Jin and his wife Chow were her neighbours in china and that her parents allowed her to follow them because they assured her parents that, they were going to take good care of her.

She admitted that, her family was poor and that her father owed her uncle and her auntie some money for a surgery performed on her father’s leg. She narrated that her father suffered injuries through an accident on his way to pick her up from school; this also resulted in her becoming a school dropout.

She disclosed that her passport and other traveling documents were secured by Jin and after meeting at shanghai she was introduced to two other girls who came to Ghana with her.

When they arrived in Ghana, the accused persons sent them to casinos but did not tell them exactly what to do. Later she was forced to sleep with a Lebanese, which was her first encounter in December 2007. She said she tried to resist the man but James severely beat her and told her he owned no restaurant. She reiterated that their slave master only made them have sex with white people and not blacks.

She also said that anytime she refused Jin’s demands, she had to pay a penalty of $ 50 a day. ‘I had no choice but to do as I was told because I could not raise that amount’ Her slave master charged $70 per night or $40 per hour for men to sleep with her but kept all the money to himself with the justification that he was using the money to settle a $6, 000 debt accumulated from her visa and air fare.

During cross- examination from counsel of the accused persons, Mr. O K Johnson, the witness told the court that, she could not tell her parent she was prostituting because it was an embarrassment.

She said even though she knew the brothel was close to the La police station, she could not report the incident for fear of her life and those of her family back in china.

However, the police are still searching for three of the victims, who were not available on the day of the raid.

Hearing continues on Saturday 15th march, 2009 where our reporter is expected to be further cross examined.

Please Stay tuned.]]></string>
    <string name="doc_title"><![CDATA[<b>SOUL TAKERS 1: DVLA Rots </b> <i>Anas Aremeyaw Anas exposes corruption at DVLA, the Ghanaian agency that grants driver’s licenses.</i>]]></string>
    <string name="chinese_sex_mafia_busted"><![CDATA[The boss of Peach Blossom Palace is spotted in Ghana’s most expensive casino, wearing Gucci shades, a golden brown Emperio Amani tuxedo and a custom-made Rolex wrist watch.  Scores of raunchy mini-skirted Chinese girls fill up his glass with exotic French champagne. He spins his cozy swivel chair in sensuous delirium as the ladies’ dainty fingers caress his neck, back and shoulders to orthopedic effect. “Ha,ha ha!” he lets out another loud peal of frenzied laughter.  There is no doubt that this imposing figure is a successful man. No doubt at all that his prosperity comes from hot sweat. What is not immediately evident though is the fact that the sweat that rakes in his millions does not flow from his own pores but from the disreputable chores of hapless naïve lasses he had made whores on the shores of West Africa; the fact that he presides over an evil empire that traffics his own Chinese compatriots, engaging them in sex slavery, not only here in Ghana, but also in Nigeria and Togo.  There is no doubt that this impressive figure is a successful man. His appearance likewise leaves little doubt that his prosperity comes from brisk business. What is not immediately evident is the fact that he rakes in millions that flow not from his own pores, but from the bloody chores of hapless, naïve lasses he has made whores on the shores of West Africa. He presides over an evil empire, which traffics his Chinese compatriots, engaging them in sex slavery, not only here in Ghana, but also in Nigeria and Togo.  The non-African expatriate community is the clientele. Peach Blossom Palace is the wholesale outlet from where the “goods” are marketed and sold. Poor, innocent and vulnerable Chinese girls, some as young as 19, are the human commodity on sale paraded in front of the clients like pieces of meat in a butcher shop window. They are lured here with promises of honest, well-paid jobs, only to have their passports and return tickets confiscated. The travel documents may be recovered, but only after one had paid off the cost – invariably inflated - of the trip to Accra. They are beaten and threatened with a high debt to be repaid only through the sale of their bodies. They are thrown into debt bondage and forced to sell their innocence and human dignity for their master’s gain in nightclubs and casinos. ‘I was told that I was going to be waitressing in a Chinese restaurant, but it however turned into nightmare. There was no way of turning back and I resorted to this dehumanizing business’ said one of the girls. Any of this trafficker’s victims, who attempt anything akin to disobedience, not to talk of rebellion, is firmly, swiftly and brutally repressed.  Six months of backbreaking investigation yielded the above discovery on the nefarious activities of King James, the man at the centre of the sex trafficking ring.  Posing as a bartender in the hotels where this sordid business is carried out, “The New Crusading Guide” reporter managed to capture every aspect of this trade with a hidden camera. He also pretended to befriend a lady who lived in the brothel and from whom, over a period of four months, he obtained valuable, first-hand accounts of the activities of King James and his colleagues. All of the above described is captured on video. It was upon the presentation of this evidence that the Police CID planned and carried out a raid on the Peach Blossom Palace in Labadi,Accra.  The United Nations Convention Against Transnational Organized Crime, Supplemental Protocol to Prevent, Suppress and Punish Trafficking in Persons, Especially Women and Children (2000) serves as the international legal standard. It outlines the definition of human trafficking in Article 3 (a):  “Trafficking in persons” shall mean the recruitment, transportation, transfer, harbouring or receipt of persons, by means of the threat or use of force or other forms of coercion, of abduction, of fraud, of deception, of the abuse of power or of a position of vulnerability or of the giving or receiving of payments or benefits to achieve the consent of a person having control over another person, for the purpose of exploitation. Exploitation shall include, at a minimum, the exploitation of the prostitution of others or other forms of sexual exploitation, forced labour or services, slavery or practices similar to slavery, servitude or the removal of organs.”  Human trafficking is the fastest growing criminal industry in the world, with total annual revenue for trafficking in persons estimated to be between $5 billion and $9 billion. The Council of Europe states that “people trafficking has reached epidemic proportions over the past decade, with a global annual market of about $42.5 billion”  Enslavement Prevention Alliance – West Africa, an NGO that has provided the victims with post-rescue care, stated that: “The ruthless criminals behind the sexual exploitation of these vulnerable women should feel the full hand of the Ghanaian law. This would not only serve to provide the victims with justice, it would also serve as a deterrent to all those who wish to perpetrate similar crimes in Ghana. Swift prosecution of this case will send a clear message that the business of sexual slavery is not welcome here.”  HOW THE COMPLEX WEB OPERATES The mafia operates from Ghana (main distributor) to Lome, Togo and Ikoye, Victoria Islands area in Lagos, Nigeria where the girls rotate. The New Crusading GUIDE has also picked up signals of the Chinese sex mafia’s strong presence in Nairobi, Kenya. “When Chinese girls are used in America they are sent down to some of these African countries for further exploitation”. Our source hinted. In Ghana, Tema, the harbour city serves as a hub for brisk business as some expatriate staff are able to hire the girls for over three months paying $200 per night. The girls with dreams of a better life, away from the grinding poverty are sometimes seen hovering around the French Embassy areas in Nigeria where pubs are located.  In all these countries, the modus operandi of beating the girls whenever they refuse to serve a client is prevalent.  Just like the locations in Accra, the Chinese sex trafficking mafia do not deal with gleaming villas’, they choose locations where people least expect them to be, to carry out their activities. The girls usually wear short skirts and look very flirty. ‘The area in La, (Ghana) where the ring operates from, has some trappings of a shanty town, it is very difficult for one to even assume that this kind of thing can happen there’ said Kester Aburam Korankye of the Cobra Eye Investigative Team.  In all these countries, the young and pretty attract more cash, our inside source who does not want to be named indicated to us in an interview. “If they are between the ages of 19 and 22, their price can be higher than $ 200 per night. Virgins can fetch over 1000 dollars, as for traffickers they go where the money is, they don’t care whether its Africa or Mongolia, the cash is most significant” our source concluded.  THE HARD CORE EVIDENCE, REPORTER POSING AS A BARTENDER MONITORING ACTIVITIES OF THE TRAFFICKER AND THE GIRLS  The undercover footage begins with a scene of an expatriate sitting on a luxurious bed in a plush hotel room with trafficker. On the same bed lies a half-naked Chinese girl, playfully running her left forefinger through her hair.  Exactly 45 seconds into the footage, the expatriate and the trafficker start a conversation on the processes involved in bringing Chinese girls to Africa. Footage of the expatriate is seen handing over 150 US dollars to trafficker as payment for the Chinese girl he brought for that evening’s pleasure. The footage continues with the reporter walking into the hotel room dressed as a bartender (wearing a black tie on a white long- sleeved shirt tucked into black trousers) with a bottle of beer on a serving tray in hand. He walks to the two men carrying the beer. At exactly 5 minutes 17 seconds into the footage, a conversation commences between the expatriate and the trafficker, which states the following:  Expatriate: How much will you pay for a girl to come here? $6,000?   Trafficker: Not $6,000 maybe less $1,000. You pay ticket, visa everything.   Expatriate: Ticket, visa everything?   Trafficker: Do you know something? After we brought one girl here, she went to the Chinese Embassy and complained that we beat her, but we didn’t mind her and I only gave her a ticket to go back to China (blah, blah, blah).   Expatriate: So you know some agents, you know some agents?  Trafficker: I know but long time  Expatriate: But you will try  Trafficker: Yes, I will try, I recall   Expatriate: How much will we pay for the agents?  Trafficker: If you know the agent, we can talk, better girl we must pay more money. Like the age is 30 years old then small money, but 22 or 23 then more money. Like $1,500  Expatriate: Not too much, not too much, what of 17 years? Seventeen years old not fine?   Trafficker: Ah not big, too young. We can bring 20 years. China will not allow you to bring young lady come here. They will check your passport and ask you this and ask you that.  ENTERS THE REPORTER DISGUISED AS A BARTENDER  Reporter: Can I please serve you the drink?  Expatriate: Would you hurry up and get lost from this room!  Reporter: I’m sorry sir, I was only….  Expatriate: Just hurry up and leave here  Reporter: Yes sir.  The expatriate shouts at the reporter to leave the room, having noticed him stealing glances at the Chinese girl who lies half-naked on the other side of the bed. “Get out of this room now!”  THE TRUMP OF DOOM, REPORTER AND THE BEFRIENDED GIRL WHO SPILLED THE BEANS  Footage begins with the reporter descending a staircase hand-in-hand with a girl. People sitting at bar tables in a dimly lit restaurant by the ocean drinking to the blast of loud music are shown for a while. This is followed by footage of the reporter ushering the girl into a seat close to the sea. At exactly 1 minute 25 seconds of footage, a conversation begins as follows:  REPORTER: So how are you?  GIRL: Fine, my people are coming tomorrow  REPORTER: You’re what?  GIRL: My people will come tomorrow  REPORTER: Yeah, yeah your people and your husband too. Where is your husband?  GIRL: He will be coming tomorrow  REPORTER: So this Chinese people, what do you cook for them?  GIRL: That boy, its all about local food. He eats rice, stew and chicken.  REPORTER; I see, so the girls, which part of china do they come from?  GIRL: That one “dea” I can’t tell oo. They are from different state. Some are even from the villages, so they know how to farm and everything. I am here and I can’t even hold a cutlass to dig a hole. As for them, they know everything about the farm.  REPORTER; But they are beautiful eeh!  GIRL: Yes, somehow.  REPORTER: So all they do is casino, casino eeh!  GIRL: They used to play it in the house  REPORTER: They used to play casino in the house?  GIRL: Yes they play it with money, when they are playing, they write something, so you can not read it.  REPORTER; Yeah! So do they really get sick?  GIRL: Yes   REPORTER; Aahhh!!  GIRL: Yes, if they feel any pains in their stomach or any part of their body, they will have to go to the hospital, for they are not like we, black men who stay in the house for long before visiting the hospital when we are sick.  REPORTER; So it’s their boss who must pay.  GIRL; Yes, there are times they not only casino, they at times prostitution, so they know what they do, sometimes the men come to the house.  REPORTER; Aahhh, so they know what they do.  GIRL: Yes, sometimes the men come to the house.  REPORTER: So when the men do it, then the men will pay.  GIRL: Yes; GHc 1.7million, (old Ghana cedis) for one night!  REPORTER: GHc 1.7million(old Ghana cedis)?  GIRL; Yes GHc 1.7 for one night oooh!! So just imagine 12 months, they are making money.  REPORTER; Aahhh, so when she takes the GHc1.7, that money must go to the boss, right!!  GIRL: Yes  REPORTER; Then, how much the boss will give them.  GIRL; The boss will give them money, as for the amount I don’t know.  REPORTER; Aahhh!!  GIRL: Eeh, at first, they gave it to them at the restaurant. But when I move to the house, I don’t see anything like that. I see the men come to the house, taking the ladies and making love with them. And I keep wondering and saying “what kind of business is this”? So one day, the boss called me and said Mary, “I am sorry, you see the business.” Then I asked “what business? Then he said, “As for the girls, they are all prostitutes, you see the men come to them! There are times they use to sleep with them in the house and sometimes take them out of the house. You pay hotel bill.  REPORTER; Aahhh  GIRL; Yes, it just like a hotel, you pay GHc20. So you spend roughly   GHc 200, when you sleep with them in the house. You bath and even eat. We give them food.   REPORTER: The job is not a good job eeh?  GIRL ; The job is not a good job at all eeh. Sometimes they will ask me, “What have you been doing at all?” and I will tell them, “Leave me alone, is it your business?” It is a restaurant and it is not open to only Chinese people but with everything going on, everybody suspect it. They can play music and shout.  REPORTER; Aahhh  GIRL ; The music is very high, so even when you are out you hear the music. My first time I hear the music, I went there to see before I work there.  REPORTER; So have you really seen a naked, eeh, me I have never seen a naked Chinese woman before ooo!!   GIRL ; Oohhh, I, yes, yes, because I am a woman.  REPORTER; So you’ve seen them naked before?  GIRL: Eeh, oooh  REPORTER; With a man?  GIRL: No. no, with a man no, they also have their special rooms.  REPORTER: The Chinese girls also have their special rooms? So how are their rooms arranged?  GIRL: They are just like students, two on one bed. Because it is two, one oom contain six beds. There are two rooms. Only two rooms  THE DRAMATIC VALANTINE’S DAY RAID OF KING JAMES\' PALACE  At exactly 8:oo am on Valentine’s Day 2009, a combined force of over eighty armed men from the Panther Unit of the Ghana Police Service and Criminal Investigative Department (CID) besieged the premises of the Peach Blossom Palace in Labadi, near La Palm Royal Beach Hotel, Accra to conduct a swift “surgical” operation.  In what can be described as a typical scene from a Hollywood thriller, policemen surrounded the brothel, as some of the men weighed down on the premises to round up and rescue the victims of human trafficking. Hundreds of onlookers filled-up the streets to catch a glimpse of the raid.  In all, seven (7) Chinese girls and a Ghanaian couple, identified as house helpers of King James, were rescued by the police. King James, who was sitting bare-chested with his wife next to him in the house, was immediately arrested by armed policemen.  Peach Blossom Palace, which from the exterior appears to be a bar, held several rooms which served as brothels for the Chinese girls. During a thorough search of the house, the police found bags filled with condoms, needles and syringes, medicines, artificial vibrator penis, wooden penis, passports, exotic pornographic movies, microphones for singing and lap dancing equipment.  The police also retrieved 14,000 US Dollars in cash and some unspecified amount of money in Chinese Yuan and Ghana Cedis from King James. According to an insider, the money was part of fees paid for the sexual exploitation of the victims in the previous week.  After putting the rescued girls on board a waiting bus, several armed policemen escorted King James and two other Chinese men (believed to be accomplices) to the waiting vehicle.  Coming soon is the interesting details of phone calls which came through to the Chinese girls which said \"we will cut your throat if you talk to anybody\".  Credit: Anas Aremeyaw Anas reported From La, Ghana, Victoria Island, Lagos,Nigeria, [Crusading Guide] ]]></string>

    <string name="soul_takers_1"><![CDATA[SOUL TAKERS UNMASKED [1]!
…Rot At DVLA To Be Exposed Tonight

Anas Aremeyaw Anas reporting from Tamale, Ghana
They were set up to license the competent and the qualified but they have their own procedures, though clearly codified, often defied.

So that instead of certifying they that possess the requisite knowledge and skills
they approve the very inept who, by sheer incompetence, innocent citizens kills.

While the honest client may be frustrated beyond endurance others, even from a distance, can their way pay without let or hindrance.

The law fiercely forbids that we to a public officer make false presentation
But alas! The very officer gospels his clients in flagrant misrepresentation;
Evangelises on how to circumvent the most hallowed convention
And also, how to go about bare-faced falsification
All this without a hint of moral trepidation

Even persons with physical disability are not denied the possibility of mechanized mobility provided they display sufficient pecuniary ability.

That the DVLA, like most of our public institutions, is infested with corruption is an open secret. The mystery though is the depth and scope of the rot. But the Tiger Eye/Crusading Guide being averse to mysteries, sent its sharp investigative lenses to penetrate the myths and establish the truths. And we dug up enough startling truths to drop even the stiffest of jaws - a disabled person, a mentally ill person, unqualified expatriates and a simple market woman without a clue about driving vicariously issued with licenses; licenses issued without recourse to critical eye test and aptitude tests or the taking of finger prints; officials instructing clients on how to make false presentations and complicit police officers creating extracts from station diaries to support false claims by applicants.

It was that easy and the cash made matters much easier. We found that officials of the DVLA were taking huge sums of money to process fake licenses for people; while other officials were ready to allow applicants to cut corners in the application process.

Ghana’s roads over the past several years have become akin to a war front, where innocent lives and properties are needlessly lost, emotions of individuals are wasted on avoidable grief and pain on a daily basis. Unfortunately, Ghanaian tax payers are funding an institution that is a key factor in this national tragedy.

Tonight at the National Theatre, the faces behind this outrage will be unmasked in the premiere of the Soul-Takers, a documentary that tells the whole story. The film premiering, an initiative of Tiger Eye in partnership with Graphic Communications Group, is a ground-breaking exposé of the deviant acts of public officials that lead to the carnage on Ghana’s roads and highways.

Archbishop Palmer-Buckle chairs the function which has President John Dramani Mahama as the Special Guest.
]]></string>
    <string name="soul_takers_2"><![CDATA[SOUL TAKERS UNMASKED[2]

    ..Officials Procure License for Cripples, Madmen, Minors etc. for Cash; No Eye Test, No Exams

Anas Aremeyaw Anas reports 37 DVLA

"Make us cherish fearless honesty."

When this line of our National Anthem was thought out, little was it suspected that it could be mischievously interpreted to extreme absurdity with unimaginable calamity; that it would be dramatized in a shamefully paradoxical manner by public officers without manners? Who could have imagined that a public officer would muster the fearless honesty to own up his corruptibility? How could our innocent forebears have conceived that a fearless and honest admission of lack of aptitude on the part of an applicant would be criminally restored to rectitude in the turpitude of the corruption-riddled driver and vehicle licencing regime? Indeed, at DVLA, they really cherish fearless honesty. No matter how illegal your mission, if you are fearless enough to make an admission , you will have somebody equally fearless to oblige you to a vile collusion; honest enough to avow his lack of compunction. It is that paradoxical.
All as a result of accidents, which have become regular features on our roads. Going by available statistics from especially the Ghana Police Service Motor Traffic and Transport Unit (MTTU), road crashes keep rising each passing day and we are all witnesses to daily media reports about such fatal crashes across the country.
Headed by our ace investigative journalist, Anas Aremeyaw Anas; the Special Investigative Team [SIT] of the New Crusading GUIDE, set out on this mission to help minimize road accidents, by particularly uncovering the artificial causes of avoidable deaths and carnage on our country’s roads.
The team focused our lenses on the following strategic areas:
• To expose fraud and rot in the issuance of licenses and other horrible dealings within the Driver and Vehicle Licensing Authority (DVLA)
• To uncover the risky attitudes of commercial drivers most of whom are entrusted with the lives and properties of members of the public, yet take alcohol before driving.
• Within the Police Motor Traffic and Transport Unit (MTTU), our mission was simple: expose the bad cops.

The DVLA was crucial to this investigation because a key function of the authority as by law stated in section 3, clause 1 is; ‘issue driving licenses.’ That legal mandate is complimented by other laws as the Road Traffic Act, 2004 (Act 683) and the Road Traffic Regulations, 2012 (LI 2180).

The Act of 2004 and Legal Instrument of 2012, gives further expatiation on the fine details that officers of the DVLA must observe in the issuance of licenses. Yet when we went undercover, we realized that the law had been side stepped by officials who took huge sums of monies to issue licenses.

37 DVLA

At 37 DVLA, known to be the heartbeat of licensing operations in the country, the investigative team managed to procure licenses a mentally challenged man, a physically challenged and a man whose picture we met right there at the premises of the DVLA.

In the case of the mentally challenged; we met Billy, an officer at the eye test section. We informed him that the man whose picture we took at Madina, was an uncle who lived outside the country and needed a local license before he returned to town.

Mr. Billy asked us to pay a sum of 250 Ghana cedis for the entire process. For starters we gave him 150 Ghana cedis and agreed to pay the remaining 100 Ghana cedis when the license was ready.

On the day of collection however, Mr. Billy directed us to pick the license from a colleague, who we paid the 100 Ghana cedis amount to. With 250 Ghana cedis, a mentally challenged we named Billa Tia John had a license processed in his name.

Still at 37, we encountered one Mr. Abu, who we negotiated to pay an amount of 400 cedis to with the promise to process a license for another mentally deranged man we met in Accra and named Jacoubs Timaya.

All Mr. Abu requested for was a passport pictures, date of birth and signature of the applicant. We paid him 300 Ghana cedis as a start and when the license was ready, we paid the balance of 100 Ghana cedis and picked our license under a tree opposite the interdenominational church at 37.
Whiles every single life lost is one too many, our nation has a long casualty list of persons lost to tragic accidents, from the very influential and famous down to the poor and peasant folk.
Prominent persons from politics, medicine, showbiz, academia and other professional fields, all of whom have become part of the scary and saddening accident fatality statistics. Amongst others:
• the three Urologists of the Korle-Bu Teaching Hospital: Professor J. M. K. Quartey, Dr. Isaac Bentsi and Dr Benjamin Osei-Wiafe Alhaji Kwadwo Mahama, Mr. Osei Kwaku, Ali Mohammed Mujahid and John Achuliwor
• Actors Kwame Owusu-Ansah and Suzzy Williams
• Young musician Terry Bonchaka
• Mr. Ferdinand Ayim; a personal assistant to a Minister
The two daughters of evangelist Eastwood Anaba also perished in a road accident, the list can go longer.
Indeed, the two surviving former presidents Jerry John Rawlings and John Agyekum Kufuor have not been spared brushes with reckless driving although they escaped unhurt on the respective occasions.
Several other people of different walks of life have been involved in life threatening crashes on our roads, many of whom till today continue to live with the resultant disability and grim memories.
In the light of all these losses, hardly does a day pass by without news reports of fatal crashes having claimed the lives of people. And with the loss of lives, careers are curtailed, dreams abruptly ended and dependants of lost ones grief for all its worth, the loss of their source of upkeep.

Beyond individual efforts at ensuring personal safety, some core state institutions have been tasked by law to maintain oversight responsibility of ensuring our safety as citizens as we go to and from our destinations.

Crucial in the very tall list of legally mandated institutions tasked with road safety and allied issues are:

• Driver and Vehicle Licensing Authority [DVLA] – established by Parliamentary Act 569 of 1999 tasked primarily to ‘establish standards and methods for the training and testing of driving instructors and drivers of motor vehicles and riders of motor cycles;’ amongst other core functions.

• The National Road Safety Commission [NRSC] – also established by law as per the National Road Safety Commission Act 1999 (Act 567), and supposed to provide strategic leadership for developing and implementing interventions and counter measures towards a sustainable management of road safety in Ghana.

• The Motor Traffic and Transport Unit [MTTU] of Ghana Police Service – are mandated to prevent and detect motor crimes and offences, prevent loss of lives and damage to property on our roads, to ensure free flow of motor traffic etc.

Other state institutions in the road safety endeavor are:

• The Ministry of Road and Transport
• The Ghana Highways Authority [GHA]
• Department of Urban Roads [DUR]
• Department of Feeder Roads [DFR]
• Roads Department of Metropolitan and District Assemblies

Every year, millions of tax payers monies are pumped into the respective institutions but the question is: has all these funds yielded any significant results?

Stay tuned for more
]]></string>
    <string name="soul_takers_3"><![CDATA[[SOULTAKERS UNMASKED (3)
The Horror Of Our Biometric Licence System And The Killing Of The Innocent

Anas Aremeyaw Anas Reports, Ho DVLA

It was designed with lofty ideals, for Ghana to rob shoulders with the civilized nations of the world. With the unique fingerprint of each individual, it is guaranteed that nobody can forge another man\'s identity. Yet the bloody claws of corruption have seeped into the veins of this ideal plan. With money, you can bypass the process and get a license that puts you in charge of lives on our roads -- whether you\'re qualified or not to drive.

During our investigation into the clandestine activities of some officials at the DVLA, we realized that in order to circumvent the ‘bureaucratic’ biometric hurdle, these officials would readily apply for and deliver learners licenses for applicants and impress on them to show up on the day of ‘capturing,’ where their pictures, finger print (usually the index or middle finger) and signatures are taken by a DVLA official.

Within minutes, a temporal license is issued and officially logged in, applicants use that document to access the roads for three months, within which time a license proper is issued (i.e. the card) or the temporal license is renewed.

Within that three month period, all genuine license applications countrywide are brought down to DVLA’s print farm here in Accra, printed and then returned to respective branches, where applicants are called to pick them up.

The focus of our investigation was to test whether officials of the DVLA were following due process in the issuance of a sensitive document as driver’s license.
Mr. Amegashie; a transport expert and former DVLA chief executive states: “let’s realize that, when we talk of driver’s license, it’s a very secured document and we need to be careful about its issuance because immediately the person gets it, he has unrestricted access to driving, let’s get that point straight,” he said.

Over the period of our investigation, we applied for and obtained licenses by cutting corners on one hand and by going through normal processes as stipulated by the DVLA regulations on the other hand.

Either way we ended up having to pay huge sums of money to get the licenses fixed even though we realized that some of them were not genuine because applicants did not go through the biometric process of acquisition and that brought to the fore the incidence of faking even within the DVLA.

The point of note here is; when people who do not merit licenses possess one, the road increasingly becomes unsafe each second. And we contend that it is such people who end up causing accidents resulting in loss of lives and property.

THE RECORDS OVER TIME

AN ANALYSIS OF MOTOR ACCIDENT RETURNS FROM CENTRAL MTTU (BETWEEN 1991 – 2012)

OBSERVATIONS
• A total number of 252,819 cases were reported between the period.
• Out of that number, fatalities were 22, 677 (9% of total number of cases)
• From 1994 till date, accident cases graduated from the 1,000s to the 10,000s
• Increase in number of cases always comes with a proportionate increase in vehicles involved.
• Accident cases are classified as follows: Fatal, Serious and Minor

Total Number of Cases (per year) = Fatal + Serious + Minor Accidents
NRSS – The National Road Safety Strategy

The three deadliest years are as follows:

2000 (14,650 cases _ 973 fatal)
2004 (14,734 cases _ 1,397 fatal)
2012 (14,914 cases _ 1,790 fatal)


The three lowest accident years
1992 (5,954 cases _ 327 fatal)
1994 (5,958 cases _ 456 fatal)
1993 (6,189cases _ 524 fatal)
Analysis based on NRSS implementation years

NRSS 1 (2001 – 2005)
NRSS 2 (2006 – 2010)
Number of cases:
64,401
60,101
Vehicles Involved
94,580
88,979
Persons Killed
7,097
7,591
Number of people injured
49,706
47,300
Fatal Case
5,578
6,134
Source: Figures provided by Central MTTU

Motor courts
Definition: These are specialized courts that deal with prosecution of road traffic offenders who are put on trial by the MTTU.

SUMMARY OF MOTOR COURT DATA(2009 – 2012)

1.  TOTAL NUMBER OF CASES REPORTED 23,907
2. TOTAL NUMBER OF CASES SENT TO COURT 17,599
3. TOTAL NUMBER OF CASES CONVICTED 12,586
4. NUMBER OF CASES AWAITING TRAIL  2,862
5.  NUMBER OF CASE UNDER INVESTIGATION  3,672
6. NUMBER OF BENCH WARRANTS ISSUED  1,274
7. NUMBER OF OFFENDERS JAILED  217
8. WARNING LETTERS ISSUED  2,636
9. NUMBER OF CASES DISCHARGED  785
10. COURT FINES AWARDED  GH¢ 2,960,253.00
11. COURT FINES PAID  GH¢ 2,931,950,00

THE PREMIERING OF SOULTAKERS

In two days, over four thousand viewers showed up at the four screenings of SOULTAKERS at the National Theatre. Representatives of government, members of the diplomatic community and throngs of patrons were among the audience. Their reactions to the film was visible as they shook in their seat to horror and avoidable carnage on our roads.

Stay tuned for more....]]></string>
    <string name="soul_takers_4"><![CDATA[SOULTAKERS 4…
DVLA 37

At the 37 branch of DVLA, which happens to be the heartbeat of licensing operations in Ghana, where one would have expected that processes would be tighter and more stringent; the team managed to get many licenses.

First; we contacted one Billy, with the request for an express license, which is a license that would take less than a week. Initially he sounded as though it was impossible but later agreed to help because we convinced him that we needed it urgently.

With this process, we were not supposed to undertake the written or take the in – traffic test and the amount he quoted was 300 Ghana cedis. We paid the amount and the license was delivered in a matter of three days.

In our second story here at 37, we took pictures of a mentally deranged man and presented them to an official under the pretext that he was a relation who was living abroad and wanted to have a local license fixed for him before he returned to town.

There again, in as much as the customer paid the agreed sum of 250 Ghana cedis, our license was delivered at an appointed time. At the same branch we fixed a license for a physically challenged man who we found begging by the roadside just because we were ready to pay the 250 Ghana cedis charge put forward by the officer.

These instances exposed a lapse in the license acquisition process with respect to the flouting of a statutory rule to do with physical presence of an applicant as required in the issuance of licenses and grievously so, at no mean a branch as the headquarters at 37.

DVLA Tema – ISSUES OF FRAUD AND FORGERY

At DVLA office in Tema, the team encountered an official called Mr. Selase. He was ready to assist an applicant to skip all processes in acquiring licenses but insisted that applicants show up to have their biometric details captured before their temporary licenses are issued.

Mr. Selase went as far as releasing official documentation to license contractorsin order to convince applicants to come and have their details captured.

One such document which we intercepted, exposed the extent to which officials of the DVLA were abusing the laws by issuing pass marks in respect of the written test, eye tests and in – traffic tests; all these tests have not been taken.

At Tema for example, the breakdown for components as we saw it on an applicant’s document summed up to 73.50 Ghana cedis. Yet the applicant had to pay 250 Ghana cedis to Mr. Selase in two tranches of 150 Ghana cedis and the remainder when he came to pick the temporal license.

The corresponding Form F 1 is usually in two parts; the first part for applicants to fill out and the other part to be completed by an optometrist or an ophthalmologist. We realized that all portions meant for applicants were usually completed by the connection officers.

Even the part meant for an ophthalmologist was also filled in right there at the DVLA even though the applicant was almost always absent during the process.

The scores for one of the applicants read as follows:

Visual acuity: (6 out of 6) for UNAIDED VR and VL.
Visual Field Assessment: ‘FULL FIELD’
Binocular Vision Assessment NAD
Medical Reports Vision is good

A date was quoted and the ‘supposed signature and stamp of the ophthalmologist/ optometrist was appended but without a stamp as was required by law.

In the end, the applicant in question has gone for the temporal license and has been issued the license proper.

DRIVING TEST WAHALA

Indeed, an area within the DVLA that was rife with extortion was the driving test. For the better part of time, instructors would take GH¢ 50 or more as bribe, in order to pass an applicant even if an applicant fails the test.

What most applicants feared was the inconvenience of time and travel that was associated with being referred in the event that they fail to get the minimum 21 marks out of 30 questions.

Several people who have failed to pay this bribe sum, ended up writing the exams for several times. One such frustrated applicant we met in Tamale recounts his ordeal at the hands of these officers when he went for a license upgrade from grade C to D.

Applicant: At some point, I decided to pass the back door; I would skip every test be it in traffic or theory test.
Tiger: It was a fair deal, isn’t it?

Applicant: Yes, I think it is good. I processed license B in Accra, the man took 250 Ghana cedis that I had to write the exams, three times I failed. I had to collude with some other guy on the fourth attempt before we passed.
Tiger: Before you passed; I see …

Applicant: Even with that I had to come and do the eye test and other things, they realized that I was going to do anything to get the license because they had my records.

It is much easier for a person who pays huge sum of money; he has a hustle free process. At least with a valid license, I would earn a living. I currently hold license C, even which one expires in 2012.

The bigger issue is how I would survive if I end up using all my salary to process a license. At least it affords me the opportunity to travel outside on ticket of the company, without a license your chances are limited.

Ho DVLA

When the investigative team got to the Ho, we were immediately pointed in the direction of Mr. Nelson, a man reputed for fixing licenses within the shortest possible time.

Unlike officials in other parts of the country, he was ready to process local licenses for expatiates provided such people avail themselves at an appointed time for their biometric details to be captured.

Like Mr. Selase of Tema DVLA, Mr. Nelson readily released official documents to license contractors to convince applicants to avail themselves on the day of capturing to complete the process.

Thanks to his hard work, we have documents indicating that four expatriates have learners’ licenses, and he is awaiting their arrival whenever they do to complete the process.

CRISSCROSSING LICENSE APPLICATIONS & FRAUDULENT DOCUMENTATION

It was also at Ho DVLA that we discovered the phenomenon where people applied for licenses in a particular office but were referred to other offices to complete the process. This is what we came to know as the crisscrossing of applications.

We applied for three licenses in respect of absentee applicants and Mr. Nelson agreed to proceed with the process if we would pay him a sum of 300 Ghana cedis in respect of each applicant.

When the learners’ licenses were ready for the three, Mr. Nelson gave us the contact of another officer at Winneba DVLA and asked that the applicants report to Winneba, where they would be required only to undergo the final processes of the application.

Whiles we were at Winneba, the team found something curious about the application document in respect of all three applicants. It was the answer to how DVLA officers applied for licenses through the back; and the process can best be described as fraudulent.

First: DVLA officers obtained official station diary extracts from the Police indicating that the particular applicant had lost his/her license.

Second: Then they proceeded to fake an old driver’s license copy with the particular picture that the applicants attached earlier.

So the particular application comes across as a license replacement rather than a fresh application. This we detected was the reason why applicants could skip all other processes.

Weija DVLA

The team also investigated some officials at DVLA branch at Weija. Here again, we found officers would insist on due process insofar as applicants were ready to avail themselves to complete the processes at the stage of issuing the temporal license.
At the center of the deals here at Weija was an official called Mr. Brako ably assisted by his cohort called Mr. Ghartey.

Although officials at Tema and Ho DVLA offices would readily release license documentation, Mr. Ghartey would not. He preferred to keep all documents till the applicants were ready to take their tests and thumbprint in Accra; a situation that again confirmed the crisscrossing of license application.

It was at Weija that we managed to process a license for popular radio presenter, AbeikuAggrey Santana, without his knowledge.

The whole episode started when we asked Mr. Brako if he could help us process a license for Abeiku, who we introduced as a neighbor.

This is what transpired:

Tiger: What about the license for Abeiku Santana; we share a wall with him and he has also misplaced his. Can you help us with that too?
Mr. Brako: Which Abeiku; the presenter?

Tiger: Yes
Mr. Brako: I do not do stuff for such people, in any case; how did he misplace his license?

Tiger: Not misplaced per se, truth is, he does not even have one at all.
Mr. Brako: So he also needs one?

Tiger: Yes he does.
Uncomfortable as he felt, Mr. Brako directed us to deal with Mr. Ghartey, another license fixing expert at Weija.

After making payment of 300 Ghana cedis to Mr. Ghartey, he gave us a provisional license of AbeikuSantana, curiously it was in the old wine coloured booklet format. Yet it bore the name and picture of AbeikuAggrey Santana.

When it got to the stage of picture capturing, signijng and thumb printing, we told Mr. Ghartey about the inability of a very busy Abeiku Santana to come personally to their offices during the weekdays.

And since DVLA offices were closed on weekends, Mr. Ghartey agreed to another person using his details to complete the process even though the name of applicant would remain unchanged.

This is what ensued between us and Mr. Ghartey:
Mr. Ghartey: So as you can see, this is his temporal document, everything has been signed, it would have been best if he could come and complete it [i.e. take picture, sign and thumbprint]
Tiger: As you know, he is very busy during the weekdays; he can make time only on weekends and as it stands you do not work on weekends too.

Mr. Ghartey: Yes, we do not work on weekends.
Tiger: I was thinking of bringing my picture to be used so that I can thumbprint in his stead.

Mr. Ghartey: Okay
Tiger: So that as and when he is ready, I would bring him to come and do his part.

Mr. Ghartey: It is a fast process that would not last even five minutes
Tiger: I know; that is the reason why I want to add some money so that his name remains and my picture is used.

Mr. Ghartey: If so, then I might as well use your name. Then wait till he comes to complete the process
Tiger: I prefer that you use my face and his name because this process has come this far.

Mr. Ghartey: Maybe you should give me your name so that I can do this for you, so that I keep this copy for him till such a time that he is available.
Tiger: Is that so? Then let me put down my details for you to proceed in that direction.

Tamale DVLA

The team had heard a lot about the Tamale DVLA branch; amongst other accolades, it was seen as the notorious branch where all kinds of illegalities were being perpetrated, and over the period of our investigations, we found these perceptions to be true.

As part of our work, we spoke to the branch director and his deputy, who exhibited full awareness of due process in the license acquisition process, yet when we went down to the offices, it was an entirely different story.

We uncovered that officials were taking huge sums of money to issue fake licenses, colluding with applicants to skip application processes for huge sums of money plus renewing and replacing licenses without recourse to the law.

By far the biggest license contractor we met at Tamale was called Nana Kwame (a.k.a. Nana Hotman) he took pride in the swift delivery of licenses.

Thanks to his ingenuity, the team managed to fix licenses for a cripple we met in Tamale, a market woman and a man whose picture we picked up from the internet.

The team paid Hotman 300 Ghana cedis for the physically challenged man’s license. Whiles that of the market woman and the other man cost the team 400 Ghana cedis each.

On one occasion we approached Nana Hotman to help us fix a license for an expatriate, our request triggered a revelation from him on the dangers associated with trying to fix local licenses for expatriates. This is what ensued:

Tiger: Can you help us with a license for a white friend in London, he is coming down very soon.

Nana Hotman: “As for a white man, Chief (Director) would not do it. The applicant must go to the DVLA head office. He must first write a letter, approval must be given and then his passport attached.

If he has not been here for more than a year too, he cannot apply. In fact, I do not want to have anything doing with white people.

Sometime back, some five Chinese came and offered me 1000 Ghana cedis (10 million) for each applicant, but chief rejected the work. They came here after failing to obtain licenses at Tarkwa, Accra, Takoradi etc.

So one of the police guards told them I could do it for them. They were ready even to pay as much as 10,000 Ghana cedis (100 million)

So they gave me fifty million for the five of them, they had been in the country for two years and had all other documents ready but chief said lest they write officially to Accra, he would not do it. I did all that I could but to no avail”

Nana Kwame continued: “A story is told of how a DVLA officer in Obuasi fixed licenses for 15 Chinese at a cost of 500 Ghana cedis for each.

One of these Chinese, went to cross the convoy of the then second lady (President Mahama’s wife). After drawing the Chinese’s attention severally he did not mind the motorcade and even insulted them on top.

He was subsequently arrested and his license seized, it turned out that at the time; he had been in Ghana for just five months. Just five months and he was having a license.

To make matters worse, a search in his car revealed that he had smoked heavily. Because of that, I do not want to have anything to do with these Chinese or expatriates seeking to get local licenses.

Chief would not do it, he would just disgrace and insult you on top. I would rather live on the little that I get in this case.”

Also at Tamale, an officer by name Abdul Aziz help us to upgrade a license at a fee of 250 Ghana cedis, whiles another called Nana Boakye also nearly aided us to fix a license for an insane man but for the insistence of the officer in charge that the man takes a test drive within the DVLA premises.

KUMASI MAIN DVLA

At some point in our investigation, the team agreed to go through the normal license acquisition process as stipulated by law. And we chose to use the Kumasi main branch for this operation.

One: We presented a valid identification card as a prerequisite to be given a form, following which we made 65 Ghana cedis payment at the bank.

Whiles at the bank to pay, we encountered some gurro boys who assured us that we needed people like them to assist us, because going through the normal means was too hectic and fraught with bureaucracy. But we persisted.

Two: We were directed on the same day to take our eye test, which we did and passed, not after we had been introduced to one Razak, who we paid a 20 Ghana cedis tip for starters. Razak was to be our guide through the process.

Three: The written test examination, and here Razak played his first significant role in helping us. As difficult as the test is reputed to be, he asked us to pay an amount of 50 Ghana cedis to a particular office.

What we had to do was to sit through the exams period and just give him our exam code after, it was with our code that he would ensure that we are given a pass mark even if we do not tick a single answer.

Four: Now was the time for the in – traffic test. Here again; due to the DVLA’s inability to provide a car for the test, Razak asked that if we could get an automatic vehicle, he could comfortably find a way of convincing his superiors that we indeed had taken and passed the exams.

If the team had managed to pass the in – traffic test, it would be left with a date to take picture, sign and thumb print then receive our temporary license. The last bit would have been a three – months wait for the license proper to be issued.

Lessons we took from this process were primarily that people within the DVLA had become stumbling blocks to due process, a typical case in point being Razak.

Also, there is a network of sorts, where Razak in our case was able to tell us who to pay and how much in order to have ‘a stroll in the park.’

It is this endemic and systemic bribery in the normal processes that leaves most customers frustrated and opting to go with the pay – as – you – go or the cash and carry process even though they have to pay bloated sums to these greedy officers.


THE LINCENSE ACQUISITION PROCEDURE

According to DVLA license acquisition rules [as contained in the Road Traffic Regulations 2012, LI 2180] regulation 26 subsections 1, 2, 3 and 4; a new applicant is eligible for a learners’ license if he/ she satisfies the following core conditions:

a. 18 years and above
b. Applicants must be physically present and produce a birth certificate or other relevant documents
c. Examined by an officer of DVLA (oral, theoretical and practical driving test.)

Yet as we found during the period of our investigation, all three basic conditions could be bypassed on the condition that a person could pay as much money as was requested by an official or by gurro boys who had links with officials at a particular branch.

The interesting thing however is that be it officials or ‘gurro boys’ they would take pains to explain to you the right process as stated in the law, then give you the other option of going in for a fake license.

Stay tuned for there are more faces to be unmasked.
]]></string>
    <string name="soul_takers_5"><![CDATA[SOUL TAKERS 5
The DVLA Rot, 7 Out Of Every 10 Licenses Are Fake.

Anas Aremeyaw Anas reports (Koforidua DVLA)

Little drops of water they say makes a mighty ocean, the systemic fraud that has engulfed the Driver and Vehicle Licensing Authority (DVLA) has led to an increment in the number of fake driving licenses; thereby making our roads suicidal.
The fraud has become a free for all enterprise due to Management’s inability to introduce new systems that will make faking difficult.

"Management is aware of the fraud, we generate enough money from our operations but we are not upgrading and changing to a more robust system because it would stop cash flow into our pockets that is why management is not changing this type of license. We all enjoy from the bribes and management is aware of that. They also take their share of the cash" said a senior officer at Ho DVLA who wanted to remain anonymous. "There was a system that was given to us for free for us to use simple mobile phones to determine genuine licenses from fake ones just last four months but we realized it is going to spoil our business so once again we kicked against it. The unfortunate thing is that people are dying as a result of our bribery activities, we create the opportunity for people to give us the bribes" he added.

LICENSE TRICKS

At some point in the investigation, we had in our possession two classes of licenses. Those that were obtained the quick way within a week or less and those obtained through due process (three months period or more) albeit for both we ended up paying huge sums of money.

It must be noted that the so called fake licence were obtained not only by "goro boy" but also officials of the DVLA
Subsequently, we decided to test the authenticity of the scores of licenses that we obtained in the course of our investigation. We handed over these licenses to a testing officer at Koforidua and the following results came out:

a. The details on some of the licenses were different from details on the DVLA’s database. By implication, officials were stealing details of valid applicants to prepare fake licenses for other people.

b. The details on other licenses we presented were nonexistent on the DVLA’s data system. In this case it meant that officers just forged numbers and codes and prepared these licenses for people –a majority of whom have access to our roads.


THE VEXED ISSUE OF ‘FAKE LICENSES’

During the course of this investigation, investigators presented licenses to officers of the DVLA. Almost all of them failed to distinguish between the genuine and the fake upon first sight. They all answered that it was only by referring to checks on their database that they could certainly check for license validity.

In an interview with the commander of the Motor Traffic and Transport Unit (MTTU) ACP Anwunbutogbe Awuni, he also confirmed their inability to attest to the genuineness of a license by just looking at the physical features.

“Currently, when I was in Accra Central, the DVLA gave us some machines and that is what we are using. You run it over the license and it will tell you that it is genuine or fake. They distributed it among us and that is what we are using.

It is very effective. There is some ultra violet light in it. So you will run it through it and you will see some features, so it was very (very) effective. I think we sent almost [about] 5000 to the regions and we kept about 3000 here and everybody has had one,” he concluded.

The former DVLA chief executive; Mr. Amegashie reaffirmed that a person (be it a DVLA officer or Police officer) cannot easily detect a fake license except when a test is run by the DVLA offices; usually when applicants come to have licenses renewed.

According to him; “When people come to renew their license, then we get to know they are fake. Now, you and I do know somewhere last year, Daily Graphic published that malaria drugs, there are fake malaria drugs in seven countries in Africa.

… and you see, if people are not diligent what happens is that, when people come to renew their license, they’ll go to the database to see whether the certificate of competency, the numbers they have [are valid].

So when people come to renew their license, they go to the data base. They don’t just renew, they make verification and that’s where we get to know that it’s fake,” he added.



THE INTERNATIONAL DRIVING PERMIT

In exception of the learners and regular drivers’ licenses, the international driving permit [IDP] was another area the team managed to explore with same results of corruption and cutting of corners.

The IDP is regulated by law (Road Traffic Regulations LI 2180) under regulation 143 sections 1 – 7. Section 1 as:

“The Licensing Authority may in accordance with the Vienna Convention 1968 issue an International Driver’s Permit to a person who is at least eighteen years old, to drive outside Ghana, if the Licensing Authority is satisfied that the person is
(a) A holder of a valid Ghanaian driving license,
(b) Competent to drive a motor vehicle of the description for which the Permit is issued,
(c) Resident in Ghana, etc.

When we got to Koforidua DVLA, though it was difficult to obtain regular licenses, we were successful in applying for an IDP with a valid local license as was required.

We managed to have an IDP done for a dead man by presenting his regular driving license to one Mr. Alex, who demanded that we pay Ghc 200 for the IDP.

After we had made payment, he managed to prepare the IDP for us but left the signature portion to be duly appended by the applicant after which he directed us on how to seal the permit.

A dead man could only possess a valid IDP if officers like Mr. Alex resort to issuing licenses to people who do not come to the offices as required.

We applied for another IDP at Tema DVLA, there we were not even required to produce a local license, because the officer just took the passport picture with required details (name, date of birth and signature) and of course his charge of Ghc 150. He gave us a date to pick up the document and duly delivered it on the said date.

The story was no different at Asante Mampong DVLA, where Mr. Appiah, a very busy official at the branch managed like the Tema official to use just details without a valid local license to process an IDP for us at the cost of Ghc 200.

On a comparative analysis of signatures on the different IDPs we secured, we found similar signatures on the IDPs. That reinforced the fact that insiders were forging signatures. Whilst on the field, we found something curious about the signature portion of the Licensing Authority: it was evident to us that officials in other branches were forging signatures of their superiors.

The rot at the DVLA is so bad that we are aware of an established trend where documents are obtained for people who neither deserve nor request for them. The situation can be likened to how Ghanaian passports and other national identification documents are owned by non-nationals through corrupt and illegal means.

Ghanaian licenses are easily obtainable thanks to the rot and fraud at most DVLA offices, the result however is that it could be used as an ID to commit a crime in a foreign country, a situation which will eventually tarnish the image of mother Ghana.

COMING UP:
In the next installment of our exposé, we put the spotlight on some reckless activities of the people in whose hands lives and property is entrusted on a daily basis. We also seek answers from the National Road Safety Commission on how to make our roads safer.

Book your copies in advance. Till then, we wish you ALL a safe journey. Do not drive tired, drive safe.
]]></string>
    <string name="soulTakersTitle1">SOUL TAKERS UNMASKED [1]</string>
    <string name="soulTakersTitle2">SOUL TAKERS UNMASKED [2]</string>
    <string name="soulTakersTitle3">SOUL TAKERS UNMASKED [3]</string>
    <string name="soulTakersTitle4">SOUL TAKERS [4]</string>
    <string name="soulTakersTitle5">SOUL TAKERS [5]</string>

</resources>